<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>nathanielbd</title>
    <link>https://nathanielbd.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content on nathanielbd</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International License.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 22 Aug 2021 17:33:48 -0600</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://nathanielbd.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>The Algorithm Built to Fail</title>
      <link>https://nathanielbd.github.io/posts/algorithm-built-to-fail/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Aug 2021 17:33:48 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nathanielbd.github.io/posts/algorithm-built-to-fail/</guid>
      <description>This is my entry for 3blue1brown&amp;rsquo;s first summer of math exposition (SoME1)
 There&amp;rsquo;s no question that elliptic curves are incredibly important to math and cryptography.
        Elliptic curve cryptography spotted in Wikipedia&amp;rsquo;s security certificate    It was the key to Andrew Wiles&amp;rsquo;s famous proof of Fermat&amp;rsquo;s Last Theorem. It was even used to fill a void in one of M. C.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Animations</title>
      <link>https://nathanielbd.github.io/animations/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Jul 2021 17:44:10 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nathanielbd.github.io/animations/</guid>
      <description>TODO: make this and change config.toml to make it visible</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Projects</title>
      <link>https://nathanielbd.github.io/projects/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Jul 2021 16:49:33 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nathanielbd.github.io/projects/</guid>
      <description>An incomplete list of some things I&amp;rsquo;ve worked on outside of jobs and school that aren&amp;rsquo;t mentioned in the blog. All of the projects have their own GitHub repository of code either on my profile or one of the organizations on my profile.
2021 I got my first industry research job!
 2020 I turned 18 years old!
WhoDaMan A multiplayer trivia game named after a classmate&amp;rsquo;s quote on Jeopardy!. I created the playable webapp, a tutorial, and open-source community version where anyone can contribute to learn by doing!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Celebrating Aleksandr Lyapunov</title>
      <link>https://nathanielbd.github.io/posts/celebrating-aleksandr-lyapunov/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 Jun 2021 16:04:16 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nathanielbd.github.io/posts/celebrating-aleksandr-lyapunov/</guid>
      <description>Happy 164th birthday, Aleksandr Lyapunov!    I recently participated in the first annual Manim math animation engine hackathon! The theme was anniversaries, so I created the above animation to celebrate the 164th anniversary of mathematician Aleksandr Lyapunov&amp;rsquo;s birth. This extended some ideas I presented from Steven Strogatz&amp;rsquo;s nonlinear dynamics textbook at the University of Minnesota&amp;rsquo;s math directed reading program symposium.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hacking the Normie Test</title>
      <link>https://nathanielbd.github.io/posts/hacking-the-normie-test/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Jan 2021 13:45:56 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nathanielbd.github.io/posts/hacking-the-normie-test/</guid>
      <description>The Normie Test is a quiz with ~40 questions that places the taker on a two-axes plot relative to internet culture personality classes like &amp;lsquo;normies&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;simps.&amp;rsquo;
        Apparently EDM is mainstream now?    Notably, the quiz is not open source and it runs on server-side PHP. How is X calculated? How is Y calculated? Why am I a &amp;lsquo;Simp&amp;rsquo; if my X-coordinate is over the line by 0.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ode to the Perceptron</title>
      <link>https://nathanielbd.github.io/posts/ode-to-the-perceptron/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Jan 2021 00:21:04 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nathanielbd.github.io/posts/ode-to-the-perceptron/</guid>
      <description>If I had to explain to someone the paradigm of deep learning, I&amp;rsquo;d start by mentioning
The Perceptron Given
\(X\), an \(n \times m\) matrix where each row \(x\) is a data vector with \(m\) features,
\(w\), a vector of \(m\) weights,
\(b\), a bias value,
define a function \(f\):
$$f(x) = \begin{cases}1 &amp;amp; \text{if } w \cdot x + b &amp;gt; 0 \\ 0 &amp;amp; \text{otherwise} \end{cases}$$
The task of predicting a class \(d\) of some row \(x\) can be solved via an iteratively improving algorithm thought to be &amp;lsquo;trained&amp;rsquo; with the data in \(X\).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Making a Portfolio Site</title>
      <link>https://nathanielbd.github.io/posts/making-a-portfolio-site/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Aug 2020 15:39:47 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nathanielbd.github.io/posts/making-a-portfolio-site/</guid>
      <description>This content was created as part of an educational workshop for SASE Labs UMN, of which I served as director from 2020-2021.
For readers of this blog:
I use KaTeX for math typesetting. When I embed GitHub gists, I add this CSS (as a Hugo partial). When the GitHub gist is a .csv file I add the following CSS:
.gist .markdown-body .csv-data th, .gist .markdown-body .csv-data td, .gist .markdown-body .csv-data .</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Unexpected Lessons from breaking Webgames</title>
      <link>https://nathanielbd.github.io/posts/breaking-webgames/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Jul 2020 18:26:45 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nathanielbd.github.io/posts/breaking-webgames/</guid>
      <description>One of the reasons I started programming was to code exploits in webgames. The other reason involves a certain 1980s text adventure, but that is a story for another day.
        Almost as sarcastic as Zork, but in first person    Looking back, I realize that this unconventional way of getting into programming exposed me to several important concepts early. Let&amp;rsquo;s look at a few from the perspective of a programming noob.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How I used Manim with WSL and data points</title>
      <link>https://nathanielbd.github.io/posts/manim-in-wsl-with-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Jun 2020 16:04:16 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nathanielbd.github.io/posts/manim-in-wsl-with-data/</guid>
      <description>I recently (last night) submitted my video entry for the Breakthrough Junior Challenge 2020, a competition for students aged 13-18 to submit a video explaining a topic in physics, life sciences, or math in a 3 minute video. In a competition filled with entries with amazing Adobe After Effects and Element 3D editors, I sought to be unique among the 10,000 competitors by using Grant Sanderson/3Blue1Brown&amp;rsquo;s math animation engine, Manim. The source code for my video can be found here.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Segue from Segways</title>
      <link>https://nathanielbd.github.io/posts/segue-from-segways/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Jun 2020 17:17:48 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nathanielbd.github.io/posts/segue-from-segways/</guid>
      <description>This content was created as part of an educational workshop for SASE Labs UMN, of which I served as director from 2020-2021. Check out the demo here.
Introduction         Polizei make Segways go brrr    Segways are pretty cool, and they can be the perfect segue into talking about control theory.
Segways need a robust mechanism for correcting itself in order to self-balance.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>https://nathanielbd.github.io/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 May 2020 11:45:23 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nathanielbd.github.io/about/</guid>
      <description>My name is Nathaniel Budijono.
I&amp;rsquo;m a life-long autodidact currently studying computer science and math at the University of Minnesota. In the future, I hope to be an interdisciplinary computational researcher using computational structural biology or computational chemistry to create technologies for health and the climate.
Right now, I am reading
 Nonlinear Dynamics and Chaos with Applications to Physics, Biology, Chemistry, and Engineering by Steven Strogatz Quantum Computation and Quantum Information by Michael Nielsen and Isaac Chuang  In the past, I have worked as a software engineer intern at Rally Health and AI research intern at Smart Information Flow Technologies.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>